So, delighted to be joined today by
Jason Arday. Jason, how are you?
I'm not too bad, thank you, Nick.
Yourself?
Yeah, good. We're just comparing off
screen camera about how frantic we both
were, which is good fun then to sit down
for 10 minutes and have a good chat.
Surviving.
Um
So, listen, let me let me let me let me
let me go straight into it kind of
you're you're
expert or whatever word that kind of
you're out there about race and equality
and education and you're professor of
this these areas.
And we live in a world where
chaos is a norm.
Are we going backwards in our
education of ourselves or actually do
see progression for ourselves?
That's a good question. I mean, I
wouldn't
we probably stagnated rather than kind
of going backwards or forwards and
sideways. We've kind of stagnated and
we're kind of submerged in a bit of a
quagmire at the moment of just toxicity,
um fractiousness, and kind of identity
politics. So, part of
the role of, you know, people trying to
mobilize this agenda in a positive way,
I guess is one to provide some stability
and two to provide some forward momentum
in terms of what we can do differently.
And I guess a lot of my work focuses on
how we can
cohesively and collectively achieve that
forward momentum.
And and is it frustrating for you or do
you feel this is part of the journey
that we're on as a society?
No, no, right. I I I I think it is but
there's a frustration that that can boil
over, but it's about how you channel
that frustration and kind of thinking
about the productivity that can come
from that frustration. And it's really
where we are as a society at the moment,
but it's this innate belief that I have,
which is almost tacit, that human beings
are capable of great things. And that
belief is what propels me to
really kind of think, okay, if we all
got our act together, we could move this
ship, we could steer it in the right
direction.
And and how do you keep the positive
I'll I'll go into more specifically, but
how do you keep the positivity going,
kind of? And what I suppose alongside
that, the question which always
fascinates fascinates me is, what kind
of what do you consider a success? And
what do you at the end of the day, what
is it when you achieve something which
is like, yeah, I've actually achieved
it?
Yeah, no, it's a great question. So, in
terms of the positivity, Nick, I guess
the thing that um
always inspires me is the fact that, you
know, there are acts of kindness, acts
of love, and acts of generosity
that do transcend, I think, you know,
which is slightly idealistic, maybe, um
the difficult things that happen in our
society. And those are the kind of
things
I try and hold on. On top of that, there
is a critical mass of people motivated
and geared towards trying to create
societal harmony. And for me, that's an
important thing. So, it's really about
aligning yourself with those people, but
at the same time, recognizing that there
will be difference, and there is there
is a friction in that that is healthy.
It is healthy for people to disagree on
things, but there are harmonious ways to
disagree, and more constructive ways to
disagree. And I think part of
my mission is really to facilitate
constructive ways of disagreement, but
more importantly, finding amicable ways
of kind of problem-solving, you know,
that benefit all of us
as a society, cuz whatever kind of views
people may have, the extremity of those
views, if you arc them
within the same shoehorn, actually
there's probably more that um unites us
in common than that divides us.
So, I I I hate to, I suppose, point
fingers, I suppose, for want of a
But do you kind of our our inability
these days to disagree
and actually debate? Do you is that a
fault of the education process that we
go through? Is that because the media
kind of categorize everything very very
black and white polarized?
I mean in in some respects the the media
is the um
conductor that that we all sing along to
or dance to. So I think the media hold a
huge responsibility in that. Um
and I think when you position identity
politics and you use fear-mongering
and you use some of the tactics that are
used to it to invoke and and stoke fear
in people um and really perpetuate
ignorance uh
then it's going to be it's going to be
problematic and that does filter into
other institutions, namely education
being one of them. And education is one
of the most primary institutions in the
UK
and or globally speaking.
And that is going to influence how
people think, how people digest
information, how people engage in
knowledge knowledge exchange. And those
things become
hugely prevalent in that kind of
discourse. So it's it's the media has a
lot to say
and we do have a media that
unfortunately in the UK is particularly
um
it's it's it's particularly aggressive I
think to to towards people trying to
mobilize change for the greater good.
So and you you mentioned education
there. Is education
does education have to um adapt and
change and push forward or
kind of or are we doing okay in the
direction we're heading?
No, I think look there there needs to be
kind of a dexterity and adaptability to
education to be able to
um pivot to the times that it's facing.
And and I think a lot of the education
we have
um in some respects um
you know minimizes aspects of history
um context that people do need to have
to be able to you know I I my belief is
the purpose of education is prepare
people to take their place within a
multicultural, multiethnic,
multi-diverse society. And what we need
to continuously question ourselves
about, you know, particularly educators,
myself included, is is this vehicle are
we using this vehicle in the best way to
prepare people to be the best global
citizens possible?
And you know, while I don't think it's
an absolute qualex, I do think that you
know, there are areas of improvement and
we do need to focus on
you know, beyond just the academic part,
how do we create um you know, how do you
this this kind of conveyor belt of
creating better human beings to take
their place in the world cuz in some
respects there is a conveyor belt nature
about education because fundamentally we
are preparing people to join the labor
market and join society. So, it's kind
of really think about how do we equip
people with that toolkit and the best
tools available and the best instruments
available to navigate the society that
they they will face. And part of that is
that you do meet a myriad of people
through varying populaces globally
speaking and it's important to have that
kind of range of thinking and that range
of inclusive thinking more importantly.
And do you think this is something that
kind of everything you've just said, is
that something that actually you look
back now and you realize
education needed to do this previously
and understand and it's only now that we
understand it or actually has the world
changed and actually education needs to
change?
No, that's and that's the thing I I I
think you know, the world has changed.
Right, I think there is so many things
politically speaking
um you know, and politics very much
dictates what happens within society and
I think that in some respects, you know,
education is has been left behind. but
part of that is the ever-changing nature
of kind of politics and the world as it
as as we as we know it almost makes it
pretty difficult for education to be
abreast of that. But, what education
does need to be, to use a rugby term, it
needs to be within a heel tap of those
kind of shifting sands in terms of the
world. So, it does need to be within a
heel tap and part of that is modernizing
beliefs and value systems as often as
possible regards to educators. And as a
society, we all need to kind of
modernize our beliefs and value systems
and also recognize the margin of error
that occurs in terms of people will
arrive at that destination in diff- at
different points.
But, importantly, there needs to be this
thinking around how do we kind of think
around ideas around belonging, identity,
who is allowed to belong, who is allowed
to identify, and who is allowed to
occupy these spaces. And it's incumbent
upon all of us to create spaces where
all types of people are able to belong
regardless of race, religion,
or any other intersectional factors. And
most importantly, that sense of
identity, it's a closed membership, and
we need to ensure that we widen the
parameters of that membership so that
all people feel a sense of inclusion in
that space.
Okay, I think on that note, it's perfect
note to say thank you so much to you for
your time and been a pleasure speaking.
Yeah, thank you so much, Nick. Thank
you.